National Council for the Traditional Arts (NCTA) collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1. National Council for the Traditional Arts (NCTA) events and other recordings, ca. 1961-2008
  - Subseries 1. Music and folklife events, ca. 1971-2008
    - Masters of Mexican Music, March-April, 2004; October-November, 2004, 67 recordings
      Eastern United States tour that presented four distinctive regional styles of Mexican music and dance.
    - Masters of the Banjo, 1993-1994, 59 recordings
      Two national tours in which seven master banjoists offered a sampling of the different styles of playing the instrument.
    - Masters of the Folk Violin, 1988-1995, 187 recordings
      Tour of Irish, Cape Breton, bluegrass, jazz, blues, and Cajun and Western longbow fiddle styles. The tours occurred in 1988, 1989, 1994, and 1995.
    - Masters of the Steel String Guitar 1990, March-April, 1990, 25 recordings
      Tours of blues, Appalachian flat-picking, Hawaiian slack key, dobro, jazz, and rockabilly guitar styles. The four tours occurred in 1990, 1991, 1993, and 1999.
    - Masters of the Steel String Guitar 1991, February-March, 1991, 19 recordings
    - Masters of the Steel String Guitar 1993, March 1993, 30 recordings
    - Masters of the Steel String Guitar 1999, October-November, 1999, 23 recordings
    - Masters of the Steel String Guitar 2000, March-July, 2000, 41 recordings
    - Memphis Sound, December 1-15, 1995, 4 recordings
      Tour in Eastern US that examined how regional folk musics in and around Memphis influenced the creation of new forms of music, such as early rockabilly and rock and roll, in the early 1950s.
    - Music from the Crooked Road, 2007, 2008, 36 recordings
      Two national tours which showcased the music of Southwest Virginia through bluegrass, mountain gospel, old-time and flatfoot dance.
    - National Folk Festival 33rd, July-August, 1971, 8 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 33rd National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 34th, July 27-29, 1972, 72 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 34th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 35th, July 26-29, 1973, 96 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 35th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 36th, August 1-4, 1974, 111 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 36th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 37th, August 1-3, 1975, 69 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 37th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 38th, July 16-18, 1976, 87 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 38th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 39th, July 29-31, 1977, 83 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 39th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 40th, July 28-30, 1978, 103 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 40th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 41st, July 28-29, 1979, 82 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 41st National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 42nd, July 11-13, 1980, 101 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 42nd National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 43rd, August 7-9, 1981, 95 recordings; 5 video recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 43rd National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 44th, July 16-18, 1982, 97 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 44th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 45th, September 23-25, 1983, 106 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 45th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 46th, September 21-23, 1984, 81 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 46th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 47th, September 20-22, 1985, 70 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 47th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 48th, July 4-6, 1986, 120 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 48th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 49th, July 24-26, 1987, 79 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 49th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 50th, July 29-31, 1988, 97 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 50th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 51st, July 28-30, 1989, 62 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 51st National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 52nd, August 31-September 2, 1990, 27 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 52nd National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 53rd, August 30-September 1, 1991, 33 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 53rd National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 54th, September 4-6, 1992, 27 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 54th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 55th, October 7-10, 1993, 45 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 55th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 56th, October 7-9, 1994, 27 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 56th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 57th, October 6-8, 1995, 29 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 57th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 58th, June 21-23, 1996, 30 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 58th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 59th, June 20-22, 1997, 32 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 59th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 60th, June 19-21, 1998, 32 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 60th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 61st, August 13-15, 1999, 47 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 61st National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 62nd, August 11-13, 2000, 49 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 62nd National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 63rd, August 10-12, 2001, 59 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 63rd National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 64th, August 23-25, 2002, 79 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 64th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 65th, August 22-24, 2003, 100 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 65th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 66th, August 27-29, 2004, 92 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 66th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 67th, October 7-9, 2005, 89 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 67th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 68th, October 13-15, 2006, 96 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 68th National Folk Festival.
    - National Folk Festival 69th, October 12-14, 2007, 98 recordings
      Recordings from various stages at the 69th National Folk Festival.
    - National Heritage Fellowship Concert, September 15, 2006, 1 recording
      Recording from the concert related to the National Heritage Fellowship Awards.
    - National Independence Day Concert 1998, June-July, 1998, 12 recordings
      Recordings from the 1998 independence day concert, as well as telephone interviews between Nick Spitzer and musical performers.
    - National Independence Day Concert 1999, July 4, 1999, 3 recordings
      Recordings from the 1999 Independence Day concert.
    - National Public Radio Broadcast, April 1, 1984, 1 recording
      Recording to appear on broadcast of All Things Considered #810918.
    - NFF Conferences Field Recording, May 20, 1961, 1 recording
      Conference related to preserving and utilizing folk heritage. This tape contains a recording of various people delivering papers, as well as discussion.
    - Ocmulgee Indian Celebration, September 21-22, 1996, 7 recordings
      Recordings from the Ocmulgee Indian Celebration at the Ocmulgee Mounds National Historical Park in Macon, Georgia.
    - Old Puncher's Reunion, May 5-29, 1983, 30 recordings
      Tour of the Southwest and West where working cowboys presented their music, stories, and poetry.
    - Perfume River Ensemble, August 1-4, 1995, 4 recordings
      Recordings of the Perfume River Ensemble, an eleven-member ensemble from Huê, Vietnam, from a two-week national tour performing their music outside of Vietnam for the first time.
    - Poets, Politicians And Other Story Tellers, December 4, 1991, 2 recordings
      Part of a series produced in conjunction with Lisner Auditorium.
    - Raíces Musicales Tour 1982, April 25-May 11, 1982, 37 recordings
      Recordings from national tour of regional styles of Mexican music and dance, including marimba, conjunto, mariachi and Veracruz jarocho, and music of the Hispanic Southwest.
    - Raíces Musicales Tour 1988, October 14-November 5, 1988, 68 recordings
    - Raíces Musicales Tour 1990, November 1-9, 1990, 20 recordings
    - Recording at Joe Wilson's home, May 9, 1994, 1 recording
    - Regatta Festival Committee Concert in Lowell, Massachusetts, March 16, 1991, 3 recordings
    - Saturday Night Sunday Morning, October 25, 1985--November 23, 1986, 75 recordings
      An African American heritage tour of blues, gospel, buckdancing, and storytelling, which toured the Southeast.
    - Silver Spring Ethnic Heritage Festival, June 13, 1999, 6 recordings
      Recordings from the Silver Spring Ethnic Heritage Festival.
    - Silver Spring International Festival, June 25, 2000, 10 recordings
      Recordings from the Silver Spring International Festival.
    - Street Singers & Minstrel Show Rascals, undated, 1 recording
      Originally recorded at National Folk Festivals and broadcast on WDUQ-FM. Hosted by Joe Wilson with Moses Williams, Rabbit Muse, J.C. Burris, Peg Leg Sam Jackson, and Harmonica Frank Floyd.
    - Tamburitzan Days, August 22-23, 1981, 16 recordings
      Recordings from Tamburitzan Days festival in Cuyahoga Falls, Ohio.
    - Teater Visafton och Bal, May 28-June 3, 1982, 21 recordings
      Tour from Seattle to Chicago of Swedish American theater, music, and dance traditions.
    - Tennessee Fiddlers Convention, July 19, 1975, 1 recording
      Live recordings with Joe Wilson hosting competition. Original tape labeled: "Mountain City, Tennessee Fiddlers Convention."
    - Voices of the Soviet Union Tour, September 5-11, 1990, 4 recordings
      Tour of Mid-Atlantic and New England states featuring a seven-voice women's vocal ensemble from the far north of the Russian Republic, a Tuvan throat singer, a Georgian male choir, and shepherd's horn duo from central Russia.
    - Washington Irish Music Festival 20th, May 26, 1996, 14 recordings
      Recordings from the 20th Washington Irish Music Festival.
    - Washington Irish Music Festival 21st, May 25, 1997, 18 recordings
      Recordings from the 21st Washington Irish Music Festival.
    - Washington Irish Music Festival 22nd, September 5-6, 1998, 49 recordings
      Recordings from the 22nd Washington Irish Music Festival.
    - Washington Irish Music Festival 23rd, September 4-5, 1999, 57 recordings
      Recordings from the 23rd Washington Irish Music Festival.
    - Washington Irish Music Festival 24th, September 2-3, 2000, 53 recordings
      Recordings from the 24th Washington Irish Music Festival.
  - Subseries 2. Field recordings, ca. 1961-2009, ca. 1961-2006
    Studio recordings, radio broadcasts, oral history interviews, rehearsals, and field recordings.
    - Advance Interview with Sarah Knott, February 2, 1965, 1 recording
      Open Mic interview and questions from the audience on National Folk Festival with Director Miss Sarah Gertrude Knott and Marshall Cleaver.
    - American Roots Radio Program, 1997-2001, 16 recordings
      Live radio broadcast at the Sylvan Theater on the Washington Monument grounds, Washington, D.C.
    - America's Master Storytellers, April 22-25, 1994, 8 recordings
      DAT labeled "America's Master Storytellers, Geneva, New York, Smith Opera House."
    - Audition Tape from D.K. Wilgus, undated, 1 recording
      Original tape labeled: "Audition Tape -- National Folk Festival from D.K. Wilgus. UCLA Folk Festival, Los Angeles, California.
    - Blues House Party, May 1, 1985, 1 recording
      House party in Oxon Hill, Maryland.
    - Blues Ladies, undated, 1 recording
      Originally recorded at the National Folk Festival and then broadcast on WDUQ-FM.
    - Cowboy Tour - Radio Spots, January 1, 1985, 1 recording
      Radio spots and recordings from the Cowboy Tour. Location/radio station unknown.
    - Dave Obey Fundraiser, 1991, 2001, 2003-2006, 10 recordings
      Fundraiser concert for Congressman David Obey.
    - Field Recording, 1961-1987, 14 recordings
    - Field Recording - Blaylock Brothers, December 3, 1980, 1 recording
    - Field Recording - Dunn Family, August 8, 1975, 1 recording
    - Field Recording - home, June 25, 1961, 1 recording
    - Field Recording - Interview w/Lillie D. Sturdivant, September 4, 1972, 1 recording
      NCTA archival recordings of musical performances. "Interesting interview with the daughter of G.B. Grayson conducted by Joe Wilson and Ken Irwin."
    - Field Recording - Live, August, 1980, 2 recordings
      NCTA archival recordings of musical performances. Recorded by Art Rosenbaum.
    - Field Recording - NFFA Benefit, May 29, 1976, 1 recording
      NCTA archival recordings of musical performances. National Folk Festival Association (NFFA) benefit concert, Reston, Virginia.
    - Field Recording - Piedmont Blues Party, May 1, 1985, 3 recordings
      NCTA archival recordings of musical performances. Home recording sessions for what was to become the documentary film, "Blues House Party," produced by Eleanor Ellis.
    - Field Recording - Possibly a Dance, undated, 1 recording
    - Field Recording - Radio Interview, May 26, 1981, 1 recording
      NCTA archival recordings of musical performances. Radio interview promoting the Vandalia Festival.
    - Field Recording - Steele- McConnell, July 18, 1963, 1 recording
    - Field Recording - Workshop, undated, 1 recording
    - Field Recording by Wilson, August, 1975, 2 recordings
    - Field recording from David A. Brose, April 30, 1994, 1 recording
      Field recordings collected by David A. Brose, likely sent to NCTA as demos for possible bookings by the NCTA.
    - Field Recording of Brownee and Chief Ellis, undated, 1 recording
    - Field Tape from Joe Wilson, July 1, 1975, 1 recording
    - Folk Tours - African-American Violin, undated, 1 recording
      Radio program.
    - Folk Tours - Cowboy Tour, undated, 1 recording
    - Folk Tours - Guitar Masters, undated, 1 recording
    - Folk Tours - Masters of Mexican Music, undated, 1 recording
    - Green Fields of America - Radio Spots, May 1, 1979, 1 recording
      Likely a broadcast supporting the 1979 Green Fields of America tour.
    - Home Recording, November 2, 1985, 2 recordings
      Unidentified NCTA archival recording.
    - Interview, undated, 1 recording
    - Interview with Deraldo Ferreira, January 10, 1992, 1 recording
      Original cassette labeled, "Interview with Deraldo Ferreira 1/92 - Afro-Brazilian capoeira." Interview is incomplete.
    - Interview with Henry Joseph, February 13, 1992, 1 recording
      Original cassette labeled, "Interview with Henry Joseph, 2/13, Haitian group Konbit."
    - Interview with Josephine Sutherland Wilson, December 25, 1977, 1 recording
      Interview with Joe Wilson and his mother, Josephine Sutherland Wilson, conducted in Kensinton, Maryland, 12/25/77.
    - Interview with Maurice Peltier, February 6, 1992, 1 recording
      Original cassette labeled "Int[erview] with Maurice Peltier, fiddle, and Jerry Proussard, guitar with harmonica, with Colette Fournier."
    - Interview with Norberto Tavares, February 15, 1992, 1 recording
      Original cassette labeled, "Interview with Norberto Taveres in New Bedford/Johnny Pina in Pawtucket."
    - Interview with Norberto Tavares & Johnny Pina, February 5, 1992, 1 recording
    - Interview with Sarah Gertrude Knott, May 4, 1966, 1 recording
      WLCY "Open Mic" interview and questions from the audience on National Folk Festival with Director Miss Sarah Gertrude Knott and Marshall Cleaver.
    - Interview with Zhentian Zhang, January 11, 1992, 3 recordings
      Original cassette labeled, "Interview with Zhentian Zhang #1." Translator is Nancy Young.
    - Interviews and Music, January 1, 1978, 1 recording
      Irish tour content.
    - Irish/Nouveau Irish, undated, 1 recording
      WDUQ-FM (Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania) radio show hosted by Joe Wilson with Joe Derrane, Peter Barnes, Brendan Mulvihill and Donna Long, Seamus Egan and Solás.
    - John and Phil Practice, April 12-13, 2001, 2 recordings
      Rehearsal recorded by Joe Wilson at the offices of the National Council for the Traditional Arts with John Cephas (guitar and vocals) and Phil Wiggins (harmonica and vocals).
    - Live recordings, July 5, 1980, 1 recording
      Recordings made by Art Rosenbaum, perhaps as a promotional tool for a booking for the National Folk Festival.
    - Music and interview, October 15, 1983, 2 recordings
      From original cassette tape: "music and interview Joe Pommerleau and Simon St. Pierre. Smyrna Mills, Maine. Session at Joe's [Wilson]"
    - National Folk Festival Sampler, undated, 1 recording
      "This tape is drawn from various National Folk Festivals."
    - National Folk Festival Conference, June 1, 1961, 4 recordings
      Recordings from the National Folk Festival Conference.
    - National Folklife Society, January 24-25, 1986, 2 recordings
      "Original cassette labeled 'Blue Ridge Mountain Band, National Folklife Society, University of Chicago, Jan 24/25, 1986. Artists and song selection also included in original notes.'"
    - National Heritage Fellowship Awards, ca. 1984-2007, 41 recordings
      Recordings of the award ceremony for the National Heritage Fellowship, a lifetime honor presented to master folk and traditional artists by the National Endowment for the Arts.
    - National Heritage Fellowship Awards - Banquet, ca. 1987-2006, 22 recordings
      Recordings from the banquet for the National Heritage Fellowship Awards.
    - National Heritage Awards Rehearsal, September 20, 2007, 1 recording
      Recording of a rehearsal for the National Heritage Awards show.
    - Old Time & One Blade of Grass, undated, 1 recording
      Recording originally recorded at National Folk Festivals and includes narration by Joe Wilson. Recordings were broadcast on WDUQ-FM.
    - Recording Session Tape 1, December 10, 1991, 1 recording
    - Recording Session Tape 2, December 10, 1991, 1 recording
    - Recording Session Tape 3, December 10, 1991, 1 recording
    - Recording Session Tape 4, December 10, 1991, 1 recording
    - Reed Martin Recording Session, January 16-17, 1977, 1 recordings
    - Rehearsal Session at Clint Howard's House, April 24, 1993, 1 recording
      Rehearsal for early Merlefest.
    - Saturday Night Sunday Morning Promo, July 17, 1976, 1 recording
      "This is a promo tape with John Cephas and Phil Wiggins advertising the Saturday Night Sunday Morning tour."
    - Sen. Robert Byrd-LOC Recording Sessions, 1975-1978, 3 recordings
      Library of Congress recordings of Senator Robert Byrd at the Library of Congress and at Senator Byrd's home. Recorded by Alan Jabbour and Carl Fleischhauer. Features Senator Byrd playing fiddle, singing, and discussing his background and how he learned a song and/or why it was important to him.
    - TASA Dinner, October 17, 1998, 1 recording
      From original DAT: "TASA Dinner, Willard Hotel, Oct 17, 1998, House of Hope, John Jackson, Wayne Henderson Band, This was recorded at a private party/good music top by Jackson."
    - Vol 1-How I Got Over - African-American Music, undated, 1 recording
      Part of a series of recordings from the National Folk Festival held in Lowell, Massachusetts, 1987-1989, and 1999. The material was compiled Joe Wilson and Tony Ziselberger and re-recorded by Pete Reiniger.
    - Vol 2-The Boys of Ballisadare - Trad Irish Music, undated, 1 recording
    - Vol 3-Fiddler's Dream - Fiddle Music Sampler, undated, 1 recording
    - Vol 5-Music of Lowell - Folk Festivals at Lowell, undated, 1 recording
    - Wayne Henderson Recording Session, February 3, 1990, 1 recording
      Wayne Henderson studio materials.
    - Worlds' Fair, July 7, 1982, 2 recordings
      Original cassette labeled "Irish Tradition with Mick Maloney, Knoxville World's Fair July 7, 1982."
- Series 2. Physical recordings documentation, ca. 1961-2009
  Includes paper materials removed from tape boxes, inventories, lists of artists, and container documentation from originl sound recording formats. Complements log sheets from events in Series 1. Folders 1-3 and 5-10 have been placed in the collection's case file.
  - NCTA archive recording artists, undated, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Inventories of digital files, 2005, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/11)
    Files delivered by NCTA to AFC.
  - Inventories of digital files, 2006, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Inventories of digital files, 2007, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Inventories of digital files, 2008, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Inventories of digital files, 2009, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Materials removed from tape boxes, undated, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/15a)
  - List of songs performed by Ledward Ka'apana, undated, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Sound recording documentation, undated (Boxes 2 through 36)
    Container documentation from original sound recording formats.
- Performer and Genre Lists
  - Appendix: Full List of Recording Artists
    List from the NCTA database includes additional performers accompanying the performers in the Primary Recording Artists list.
  - Primary Recording Artists
    List of main recording artists who performed for each event. The names are extracted from the "Recording Artists" field of the NCTA database. See Access and Restrictions section for more information about the NCTA database. The list is provided to show the range of performers represented in the collection. See Appendix: Full List of Recording Artists for additional performers accompanying the performers in this list.
  - Genres
    List of styles and genres of music, dance, storytelling, and crafts assigned to each performer in the collection. The terms are extracted from the "Music Categories" field of the NCTA database. The list is provided to show the types of classification that NCTA's events covered. Nearly every recording and track has at least one of these terms applied to it. See Access and Restrictions section for more information about the NCTA database.
Primary Recording Artists
The following is a list extracted from the "Recording Artists" field of the NCTA database. See Access and Restrictions section for more information about the NCTA database. The list is provided to show the range of musicians and bands represented in the collection. See Appendix: Recording Artists for additional performers accompanying the musicians and bands in this list, as well as instrumentation.
Aaron & Patrick Olwell
Aaron Flagg Quartet
Abernathy, Barry
Abshire, McGee and Courville
Abyssinians, The
Adams, Rich
Adams, Shelia Kay
Addy
African American Songsters
African Roots
Afro-American Rhythms
Agustin Lira
Ahah Highlanders
Ahimsa Youth Organization
Ái Hoa
Ain't Bad Backup Band
Akason, Eli
Akchin, Amry
Akwesasne Mohawk Singers
Alan Shavarsh Bardezbanian Middle Eastern Ensemble
Albert Hash Memorial Band
Albert, Margo
Albert, Victor
Albert, Victor
Alexander, Jane
Algiers Brass Band
Alindato, Juan
Aling, Ralph and Dick Swain